<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Nationall Assembly of Scotland, with the oath taken by the Parliament men, &amp;c. Printed at Edinburgh, by James Bryson, 1641. Whereunto is annexed his most gracious Majesties speech, to the Parliament of Scotland, the 17. of August. 1641.</title>
            <title>In the Nationall Assemblie at Edinburgh the fourth day of August, 1641</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79739</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4231BB</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E199_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E199_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E199_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17370</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860180</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860180</idno>
            <idno type="VID">157509</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79739)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157509)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 35:E199[10], 35:E199[11], 35:E199[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Nationall Assembly of Scotland, with the oath taken by the Parliament men, &amp;c. Printed at Edinburgh, by James Bryson, 1641. Whereunto is annexed his most gracious Majesties speech, to the Parliament of Scotland, the 17. of August. 1641.</title>
                  <title>In the Nationall Assemblie at Edinburgh the fourth day of August, 1641</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I). aut</author>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 6 [i.e. 7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Favvcet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLI. [1641]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Previously published with title: "In the nationall assemblie ..".</note>
                  <note>Thomason E.199[10] has caption title: "In the National Assembly at Edinburgh, the 4. day of August, 1641.". Thomason E.199[11] has caption title: "The oath to be taken by all members of the Parliament, 1641..". Thomason E.199[12] has caption title: "The Kings speech to the Parliament of Scotland, the 17. of August, 1641.".</note>
                  <note>Text continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Page 6 is misnumbered 7.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:157509:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:157509:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <p>THE NATIONALL ASSEMBLY OF SCOTLAND, WITH The OATH taken by the Parliament men, &amp;c. Printed at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by <hi>James Bryſon,</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p>WHEREUNTO Is annexed his moſt gracious <hi>Majeſties</hi> SPEECH, To the PARLIAMENT of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the 17. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1641.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>C R</p>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by T. FAVVCET. MDCXLI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:157509:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
            <head>In the Nationall Aſſembly at <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> day of <hi>Auguſt, 1641.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Aſſembly ſeriouſly conſidering the preſent caſe and condition of this Kirk and Kingdome, what great things the Lord hath done for us; eſpecially ſince the renuing of our Covenant, notwithſtanding our former back-ſlydings and defection: And if we ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becomeremiſſe in the duties of pietie, or ſhall not conſtantly hold and keepe our <hi>Religion,</hi> unto which wee have bound our ſelves ſo ſtraitly and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly, what diſhonour wee doe unto the name of God before men, who have their eyes upon us, and how great judgement wee bring upon our ſelves. Upon theſe and the like conſiderations, The Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly doth find it moſt neceſſary to ſtir up themſelves and to provoke all others, both Miniſters and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all degrees, not only to the religious exerciſes of publick worſhip in the congregation, and private worſhip in their families, and of every one by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves apart; but alſo to the duties of mutuall edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, by inſtruction, admonition, exhorting one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to forwardneſſe in Religion, and comforting one another in whatſoever diſtreſſe, and that in all their meetings, whether in the way of civil conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, or by reaſon of their particular callings, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other occaſions offered by divine providence, no corrupt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication proceed out of their mouth,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:157509:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->but that which is good to the uſe of edifying, that it may miniſter grace unto the hearers.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the moanes have been, and may ſtill be deſpiſed or abuſed, and particularly the duty of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall edification, which have been ſo little in uſe, and ſo few know to practiſe in the right manner, may be upon the one part ſubject to the mocking of ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and worldly men, who can not endure that in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which they are not willing to practiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And upon the other part, to many errors and abuſes, which the godly through their weakeneſſe may fall, or, by the craftineſſe of others, may bee drawn into, Such as are errour, hereſie, ſchiſme, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall, ſelf-conceit, and deſpiſing of others, preſuming above the common calling of Chriſtians, and uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that which is proper to the Paſtoral vocation, contempt, or miſ-regard of the publick means, idle and unprofitable queſtions, which edifie not, uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable cenſurings, neglect of duties in particular cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, buſineſſe in other mens matters and callings, and many ſuch evils in doctrine, charity, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which have dolefully rent the bowels of other Kirks, to the great prejudice of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Aſſembly moved with the zeale of God againſt all abuſes and corruptions, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their manifold obligation, moſt earneſtly deſiring, and thirſting to promove the worke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and to have the comfort and power of true godlineſſe ſenſible to every ſoule, and Religion to be univerſally practiſed in every family, and by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very perſon at all occaſions, doth charge all the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and members of this Kirk, whom they doe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:157509:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->repreſent, that according to their ſeverall places and vocations, they endeavour to ſuppreſſe all impiety, and mocking of religious exerciſes; eſpeciall of ſuch as put foule aſperſions and factious, or odious names upon the godly; and upon the other part, that in the feare of God they be aware, and ſpiritually wiſe, that under the name and pretext of religious exerciſes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe lawfull and neceſſary, they fall not into the aforeſaid abuſes; and ſpecially that they eſchew all meetings which are apt to breed errour, ſcandall, ſchiſme, neglect of duties and particular callings, And ſuch other evils as are the works not of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but of the fleſh, and are contrary to truth and peace; and that the Presbyteries and Synods have a care to take order with ſuch as tranſgreſſe the one way or other.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Aſſembly at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the 6. day of Anguſt. <hi>1641.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SInce it hath pleaſed God to vouchſafe us the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of yearely Generall Aſſemblies, It is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained according to the Acts of the Aſſembly at <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinburgh,</hi> 1639. and at <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> 1640. That no novation in Doctrine, worſhip or Government bee brought in or practiſed in this Kirk, unleſſe it be firſt propounded, examined and allowed in the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly: and that trangreſſours in this kind bee cenſured by Presbyteries and Synodes.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
